<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A problem concerning the gout in a letter to Sir John Gordon ... / by G.P., with a reply and censure thereupon.</title>
            <author>Philips, George, 1599?-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54706</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2027B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33401</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13292360</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13292360</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98852</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54706)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98852)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1039:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A problem concerning the gout in a letter to Sir John Gordon ... / by G.P., with a reply and censure thereupon.</title>
                  <author>Philips, George, 1599?-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Timothy Goodwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed and dated on p. 11: G. Philips, Novemb. 3, 1690.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gout --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98852:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98852:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PROBLEM CONCERNING THE GOUT: IN A LETTER TO Sir <hi>JOHN GORDON,</hi> Fellow of the Royal College of Phyſicians, and of the Royal Society in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>G. P.</hi> Eſq;</p>
            <p>WITH A REPLY, and CENSURE thereupon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Timothy Goodwin,</hi> at the <hi>Maiden-head</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt St. <hi>Dunſtan's Church</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:98852:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98852:2"/>
            <head>A PROBLEM Concerning the GOUT. IN A Letter to Sir <hi>JOHN GORDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OU have, by the very <hi>Magic</hi> of your moſt ingenious Diſcourſe, (with which you honored me the other day) wrought a <hi>Cure</hi> very foreign to your Profeſſion; you have rectifi'd the <hi>habit of my Mind,</hi> and expell'd a noxious Error from my <hi>Judgment.</hi> But give me leave to tell you, If you accuſtom your ſelf to ſuch Methods, if you are at ſuch Expence of Learning and Rhetoric, to undermine a ſandy Notion, to break a brittle Fancy in pieces, you will make the number of your <hi>Opponents</hi> exceed that of your <hi>Converts;</hi> either by ſtirring up ſome fumes of Pride in ſuch as I am, to obſerve our crude Conceits worthy of your Cenſure; or by raiſing an <hi>Itch of Contradiction,</hi> only
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98852:3"/>to enjoy the <hi>pleaſure of your Confutation.</hi> And now, to make my ſubmiſſion complete, I will preſent you with the Scheme of my Conceptions on that Subject, that ſo having rid my Thoughts of the burthen of them, they may credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably expire under the Honor of your <hi>Correction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have been acquainted with the <hi>GO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T</hi> near twenty years, during which time the troubleſom (but, as I have uſed to treat him, not very chargeable) Gueſt hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly paid me a Viſit once in the year, and ſometime twice; therefore I may be allowed to give an Account of it more than notionally and theoretically. And tho I do not in the leaſt pretend to any Knowledge or Judgment in the Noble Science of <hi>Phyſick;</hi> yet having in my younger years been converſant in the moſt delightful Study of <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy,</hi> I came to underſtand the Inſide of my ſelf, and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to know, and with ſome aſtoniſhment to admire that orderly and ſtupendious Contexture of all parts of the Body, which no Hand, but that of an Omnipotent Creator, could effect; which every man carries about him, but few know, and none can underſtand, but ſuch as have been accuſtomed to Diſſection, and eſpecially of living Bodies; and is in ſome meaſure repreſented by a Clock, the Order and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of which is very admirable; but when you open the Doors, and behold the Motions (ſo like to Animal) the Harmony and Subſerviency of each Wheel and Part to the other, all wonder of the Out-ſide ceaſeth, and is diſregard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Beſides, my Age warrants me to claim the Title of a <hi>Phyſician,</hi> in my own defence, that I may avoid the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thet of a <hi>Fool;</hi> and I am obliged to pretend to ſome Profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency, that I may eſcape the Cenſure of <hi>talking like an Apothecary.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98852:3"/>
            <p>Upon the whole, I do obſerve, That the <hi>Cauſes</hi> of that Diſtemper are as much miſtaken, and as little underſtood, as the <hi>Cure.</hi> Wherefore I am in my Opinion very hetero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, and do think, That whoſoever is ſo fortunate as to be affected with the <hi>Gout,</hi> (eſpecially if the Indications of it do commence in his declining Age), he ought to uſe no means to repel it, or be rid of it, but patiently to endure the Fit, as a lucky, tho ſharp Compoſition for more fatal Maladies: as I have heard or read of a Cuſtom uſed in the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> That when a Man after Fifty falls into the <hi>Gout,</hi> his Friends come about him, they make a Feaſt, and rejoice at this hopeful prolongation of his Life, and a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable addition of Twenty or Thirty years to it. And by the way, I cannot but obſerve to you, That when <hi>Aſa King of</hi> Judah <hi>was diſeaſed in his Feet</hi> (which is by all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted to be the <hi>Gout</hi>) it is noted of him, <hi>That he did not ſeek to the Lord, but to his Phyſicians;</hi> he did not patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endure the Fit, but tamper'd with <hi>Plaiſters</hi> and <hi>Pultiſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſome Perſons the <hi>Gout</hi> is <hi>Hereditary,</hi> and in ſome it is <hi>Original;</hi> and tho it be ordinary to impute the Aſſaults of it to Exceſs in Diet, and other inordinate Pleaſures; yet having in my Obſervations remark'd how many Men and Women of the ſtricteſt Temperance, and ſingularly abſtemious, have been in the moſt miſerable manner af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with it, while others, ſetting no Limits to their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, have for many Years indulged themſelves in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, yet never ſuffer'd in any Symptoms of it; I cannot be perſuaded that it proceeds naturally, or neceſſarily from ſuch Cauſes.</p>
            <p>It may juſtly and reaſonably be called, <hi>Malae Cauſae bonus Effectus;</hi> and tho poſſibly it were good for a man not to have that Diſorder in the Humours, which doth occaſion that Diſtemper; yet it is better to have that irregularity
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98852:4"/>diſpell'd by a Fit of the <hi>Gout,</hi> than to be fixed by a Diſeaſe in any of the Noble Parts, or transformed into an acute Fever; it may be well for a man to be of ſo athletic a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, as to have no Diſpoſition to the <hi>Gout;</hi> but it is certainly better for him that once hath had it, not to miſs the Annual Return of it; nay I am almoſt induced to ſay, that the <hi>Gout</hi> is ſo fas from being a <hi>Diſeaſe,</hi> that it is rather a <hi>Cure,</hi> a Cure adminiſtred by Nature, without the aid of a Phyſician, and infallibly effectual, if not interrupted by croſs and churliſh Applications.</p>
            <p>I am of Opinion, That this may be a proper Definition of the Gout, <hi>Arthritis eſt Purgatio Nervorum.</hi> And I am inclined to ſuppoſe ſo, by Reaſons drawn from my own Obſervation and Experience. Firſt, Becauſe a Dulneſs of the Brain, and Heavineſs in the Head (which is the Root of the Nerves) is a certain, if not a conſtant, preceda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Symptom of an approaching Fit; and then when the <hi>Gout</hi> is fixed in the Hand, or Foot, or other Joint, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately that Cloud which darkned the Brain, is diſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; and the Underſtanding, Memory, and Fancy, is ſenſibly clear'd and quickned. Secondly, Another Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptom is <hi>Motio formicans,</hi> a little ſtirring in the Back, like the crawling of Emmets or Piſmires; which ſeems to be a Goutiſh Humour paſſing along the Spinal Marrow, from whence the Nerves are diſſeminated. Thirdly, Becauſe the Operation, or affliction of the <hi>Gout,</hi> is not exercis'd on the Fleſhy and Muſculous Parts of the Body, but is ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly darted and conveyed through the Channels of the <hi>Nerves</hi> into ſome Joint, and yet doth not remain in the <hi>Nerves;</hi> which I conceive to be performed thus; A <hi>Nerve</hi> being compoſed of many filaments covered with a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane, is the proper Vehicle, and Inſtrument both of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and <hi>Senſation,</hi> the latter whereof is performed by the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98852:4"/>Object being carried by a tremulous Motion up to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Senſe (as a ſtretched Lute-ſtring trembles at the top, when touch'd at the bottom); the other by conveying the Animal Spirits between the Cavities of thoſe Threads or Filaments, which compoſe the <hi>Nerve,</hi> (as a Bundle of Quills clapt together muſt leave Spaces and Vacuities, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are round, and can touch one another but in <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neâ,</hi> by reaſon of their Convexity); now through theſe Cavities, I ſuppoſe, the malignant Ferment which Nature throws off, (and is the very <hi>Elixir</hi> of contagious Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours) channels along, and paſſes to the Joints, where if undiſturbed by violent and unneceſſary Applications, it gently evaporates by inſenſible <hi>Perſpiration,</hi> after its due <hi>Criſis</hi> and <hi>Periods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Becauſe the <hi>Gout,</hi> like other acute Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, hath its gradual and regular Proceſſion, its <hi>Increment, State,</hi> and <hi>Declenſion;</hi> and having gone through the Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of the Body, paſſes off (if not check'd and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul'd by <hi>Plaiſters, Salves,</hi> and <hi>Poultiſes</hi>) leaving the Joint or Member free from all Pain, but weak, and diſabled from Motion, which is the proper employment of the <hi>Nerves</hi> and <hi>Muſcles.</hi> Fifthly, Becauſe the <hi>Cramp</hi> (which is a convulſive Motion and Diſtortion of the <hi>Nerves</hi> and <hi>Muſcles</hi>) is conſtantly an Uſher, or an Attendant of the <hi>Gout.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Tenets of <hi>Religion,</hi> I deſire to be always <hi>Orthodox;</hi> in the Diſquiſitions of <hi>Natural Philoſophy,</hi> I take a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to be <hi>Heretical:</hi> I ſubſcribe to the Dictates of the <hi>Church;</hi> but I am not aſham'd to be a <hi>Non-Conformiſt</hi> to the Theorems of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and <hi>Gallen.</hi> So being once got out of the common Road, give me leave to ramble a little, and to preſent you with ſome other Notions, which without arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance I may call my own, ſince as no other man (to the beſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98852:5"/>of my knowledge) ever publiſhed the ſame; ſo peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture no man elſe will applaud, or abet: but for that I am no way concern'd; what I write, is for my own pleaſure, and your diverſion, and I am not at all ambitious to be the Leader of a Sect, or Party.</p>
            <p>I am of opinion, That the <hi>Gout</hi> and <hi>Stone</hi> are one and the ſame, conceived and begot by the ſame Cauſes, foſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and cheriſhed by the ſame Accidents, and only differing in their Seat and Poſition: the one ravaging among the Joynts, and external parts of the Body; the other making its reſidence in the inward Receſſes of the Veins, and urinary Paſſages. I take the Stomach to be the <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum mobile,</hi> and principal Agent in theſe Occurrences, to whoſe Indiſpoſition and male adminiſtration the dolorous Conſequences both of the One and the Other are primari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be attributed: ſo that the Errors in the firſt Concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (whether ariſing from the natural debility of that Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, or fomented by the inordinate uſe, and the irregulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Diet) are the <hi>Embrio,</hi> or Seed-plot, from whence the Maladies and Diſorders which infeſt the Body, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived. Hence <hi>Agues</hi> and <hi>Feavers</hi> receive the firſt Rudiments of their Formation, from the crude Relics of <hi>Indigeſtion.</hi> Here, by <hi>precipitated Concoction,</hi> the pure and genuine <hi>Chyle</hi> is perverted into acrimonious Humours, and Choler aduſt, which become the original of <hi>Catarrhs, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions,</hi> and <hi>Hydropick Diſtempers.</hi> But if by the Strength of Nature, and the Pancratic Conſtitution of the Party, the Malignity be removed from the Vitals, and the Venom precluded from channelling in the <hi>Arteries;</hi> then the <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> or <hi>morbific Salt,</hi> is forced away, and either ejaculated into the <hi>Nerves,</hi> which cauſeth the Paroxyſms of the <hi>Gout;</hi> or tranſmitted into the Kidneys, and cauſeth the conden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>Gravel,</hi> which carrieth the Contagion off with it,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98852:5"/>if ſeaſonably expell'd; but if fixed, engendreth the <hi>Stone,</hi> and the fatal Torments that attend it. Nay, the very end and utmoſt Effort, both of <hi>Stone</hi> and <hi>Gout,</hi> conclude in a <hi>ſandy and calculous Accretion;</hi> the one viſible in the <hi>Bladder,</hi> the other apparent in <hi>chalky, topaceous Stones</hi> in the Joynts of the <hi>Hand and Feet:</hi> To which, let me add the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Dr. <hi>Willis,</hi> (which I have read in his Works) that having by powerful Phyſic driven away the <hi>Gravel</hi> from a Patient, he became preſently afflicted with the <hi>Gout;</hi> and having forced that to depart, the <hi>Stone</hi> immediately returned, and became his Bane.</p>
            <p>But, what if I ſhould ſtrain a Point higher, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain you with a Fancy juſt now come into my head? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe every Man (who is not taken away by a violent Death) is ſaid to dye of a <hi>Fever;</hi> why may it not be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally conjectur'd, that the moſt Notorious, Ordinary, and Epidemical Diſtempers and Diſeaſes, are but ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diverſified Kinds, or Species of <hi>Fevers?</hi> And if ſo, then I may be allowed to Coyn a new Diſtinction, and divide that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Miniſter of Death</hi> into theſe ſeveral Claſſes, <hi>Febris Venalis, Febris Arterialis, Febris Stomachica, Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris Nephritica,</hi> and <hi>Febris Nervea.</hi> Under the firſt, I place <hi>Pleuriſies,</hi> and other Diſtempers ariſing from redundancy, or an ill habit of the Blood. In the ſecond, are compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended <hi>Agues, violent and malignant Fevers,</hi> proceeding from Inflamations, and Corruption of the Fountain of Blood and Animal Spirits, the Heart. The third ſhews it ſelf in <hi>Colics, Iliac Paſſions, Griping of the Guts,</hi> and other Torments cauſed by Wind, and fetching their Original from the Stomach. The ſharp twinges of the <hi>Gravel,</hi> and excruciating Miſeries of the <hi>Stone,</hi> are excerciſed on the <hi>Kidneys, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>reters,</hi> and <hi>Bladder,</hi> and may fairly paſs under the Denomination of <hi>Febris Nephritica.</hi> And doubtleſs the Pains and Afflictions of the <hi>Gout,</hi> may properly be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98852:6"/>
               <hi>Febris Nervea,</hi> ſince its Swing and Operation is wholly in the <hi>Nerves,</hi> and is indicated and determin'd by periodical and feveriſh Fits; a true Fit of the <hi>Gout</hi> being always attended by a <hi>Febricula,</hi> or ſhort Fever. Thus the Body of Man is aſſaulted by Enemies of its own Generation; one ſort of Fever ſtorms it, another blows it up, another undermines it; this batters it, and that pulls it to the ground; every Man deſires to <hi>live long,</hi> but no Man would be <hi>Old;</hi> and even the <hi>Gout,</hi> which generally is the Conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitant of old Age, helps to increaſe the Miſeries of it. I will conclude with a Fable of the <hi>Gout</hi> and the <hi>Spider,</hi> which was told me by a Country Gardiner. The <hi>Gout</hi> and the <hi>Spider</hi> (having been old acquaintance) met in a Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers Evening; and after ordinary Salutations, began to congratulate each other's Felicity. The <hi>Gout</hi> extoll'd his good Fortune, that was ſo luckily placed in a ſtately Houſe near adjoyning, where the owner of it careſſed him with all manner of kindneſs, comforting him with <hi>Plaiſters,</hi> refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him with <hi>Oyl and Frictions,</hi> covering him with <hi>Scarlet</hi> and <hi>Flannen,</hi> and treating him with ſo much Civility, that he was not put to the toil of walking, but reſted Day and Night in a warm Room. The <hi>Spider</hi> ſaid, I have taken up my Quarters in a poor Man's Cottage, where tho my En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment be but mean, yet I enjoy Safety and Tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; I ſpread my Nets through the Houſe, I have as many Webs in the Loom, as would ſerve all my Generation, and no Body diſturbs me. Thus having mutually diſcanted on their Happineſs, a curioſity prickt them to change Quarters for one Night, that each might be a Witneſs of the other's good Condition; ſo they parted, appointing to meet in the ſame place, and recount their Adventures. Accordingly the <hi>Gout</hi> marcheth to the Cottage, attacks the Owner, and fixeth his Reſidence in his <hi>Great Toe.</hi> The <hi>Spider</hi> aſcends the Gentleman's Parlour, falls preſently to work, and before day
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98852:6"/>he had extended his <hi>Manufacture</hi> through all the Spaces of the Room. The next Night they met again, but in a moſt deplorable Condition; the <hi>Gout</hi> look'd as if he were <hi>half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drown'd</hi> and <hi>half-dead.</hi> The <hi>Spider,</hi> as if he were <hi>frightned</hi> out of his Wits. But wondring a while at one another's Fate, and recollecting themſelves, the <hi>Gout</hi> told his Friend, That when he came to the Cottage, he (according to his Cuſtom) ſeized on the Good man's <hi>Toe,</hi> expecting to reſt quietly there; but to his Aſtoniſhment, the Man ſtarted up, run about with his naked Feet, and plunged himſelf into a <hi>Pond,</hi> and had almoſt drowned or choak'd him, ſo that he had hardly eſcaped with Life. My Fortune has been little better (replies the <hi>Spider);</hi> for having finiſhed my Work, and ſpread my Nets up and down the Room, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took me to reſt; but early in the Morning the Chamber-Maid comes, and with her <hi>Broom and Whisk</hi> un-merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroys and tears down what I had wrought; I, upon the Alarm retreated into a Hole, and with much difficulty made my eſcape hither. So after a little pauſing, they took leave: <hi>The</hi> Gout <hi>returning to the Rich Man, and the</hi> Spider <hi>to the Poor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But leſt the flat Repetition of ſuch frivolous, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coherent Stuff may prove as troubleſom as the Diſeaſe it treats of; or the wanton Excurſions of my Pen prove equally Vexatious to the very Twinges of the <hi>Gout;</hi> In pure Pity, and good Manners, I deſiſt, after I have with all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Reſpect and Sincerity, avowed my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Novemb.</hi> 3. 1690.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Faithful Humble Servant, <hi>G. PHILIPS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:98852:7"/>
            <head>The REPLY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THo' by your Letter you do me the Honour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent me as moulded in that of the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſive Friendſhip; and ſubmit to my Reflections your very ingenious and well-contrived thoughts of the Cauſe, previous and ſubſequent <hi>Phoenomena</hi> of your old and intimate Friend, <hi>the Gout:</hi> yet I will not be guilty of ſo much Vanity, as to endeavour any altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in that <hi>Scheme</hi> which you have ſo neatly and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſly framed: Eſpecially your Sentiments on that Head, being eſpouſed and very well defended, not only by <hi>Juncken,</hi> and thoſe Learned Phyſicians, who will have the <hi>Nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious juices</hi> to be conveyed to all the parts of the Body by the <hi>Nerves;</hi> but alſo by that Ornament of Learning, Dr. <hi>Charleton,</hi> preſent Preſident of the Royal College of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians; for whoſe Learning and acute Reaſonings, I have that veneration, that I judge it almoſt a Crime to entertain different Sentiments from his, in ſuch Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. But I muſt add, without the leaſt flattery, That if any inducements could oblige me to become a <hi>Proſelyte</hi> to the ſpeculative part of your Opinions on this Subject, you your ſelf furniſh me with ſtronger inducements than all my Books or Converſe in the World could do. For when I conſider the heigth of your Fancy, the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your Reaſonings, the ſolidneſs of your Judgement, the great connexion I find betwixt all the Links of the Chain of your various and pleaſing Thoughts on all Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; the charmingneſs and peculiar neatneſs of your
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98852:7"/>Pen, I am almoſt perſuaded to believe, that the <hi>Gout</hi> muſt be a critical evacuation of the Brain and Animal Spirits, by which Hetrogeneous, Acid, Acrious, Auſtere, and other troubleſom Particles are thrown off from the <hi>Brain</hi> and <hi>Nerves,</hi> on the Articulations of the Limbs, which clouds the Fancy, and lames the Reaſonings of moſt Men who are ſtrangers to that Troubleſome, tho Advantageous <hi>Criſe:</hi> And I muſt tell you, that, were I confident <hi>your old Friend</hi> would procure me thoſe Advantages I admire in you, I would almoſt court his intimate familiarity; but, <hi>Ex quovis Ligno non fit Mercurius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe who will have the Cauſe of the <hi>Gout</hi> to be lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed immediately in the Blood and circulating Liquors, and not in the Brain, and <hi>Genus Nervoſum,</hi> and will have the Criſe performed by the mediation of the Mucilaginous and Oleaginous Glands of the Joynts, ſeem to plead fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; and are expoſed to ſewer intricacies, and leſs diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties than the Patrons of the other <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> are; and give a clear and very intelligible account of the Genea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies of all the Antecedent, Concomitant, and Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent <hi>Phoenomena</hi> of that troubleſome Companion; and leſt a Man of your Univerſal Knowledg ſhould be a Stranger to ſo uſeful a part of <hi>Anatomy,</hi> I preſume to recommend to your peruſal a little Tract, called, <hi>Oſteo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logia Nova,</hi> lately wrote by Dr. <hi>Havers,</hi> from whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Pen the Commonwealth of Learning may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect what may be uſeful to that Republick.</p>
            <p>But not to trouble you further with Speculations of this kind (for in framing, extending, and improving of fine Thoughts, I willingly and juſtly reſign in your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours the right hand of Fellowſhip) I find, not only by throughly conſidering the animal oeconomy, but by many years practice and experience, that thoſe different <hi>Hypotheſes</hi> forces very little alteration on the rational
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98852:8"/>method of Cure: And you muſt pardon me, if I take you in task as to what concerns the practical part of your Letter, if in good <hi>Scotch</hi> (I pretend not to write <hi>Engliſh</hi>) I may ſo term it; that being a Province to which I am not altogether a ſtranger.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, I muſt tell you, It's my Opinion, had a Man of your Head made it his buſineſs to be ſo much converſant in the <hi>Practical</hi> part of Medicine, as you are in the <hi>Theorick,</hi> you might have eaſily, not only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted your ſelf to the Dignity and Title of a ſecond <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> but alſo, (I am confident) you had altogether altered your Sentiments as to the Cure or Removal of your old Friend. I could (were it neceſſary) adduce many Inſtances, and poſſibly of your <hi>Countrymen,</hi> of whom ſome are on this place, others returned to <hi>Ireland,</hi> whom in a little time, by the uſe of <hi>Internals</hi> and <hi>Topicks,</hi> I freed from that troubleſome diſtemper, and not returned as yet.</p>
            <p>But in the next place, you may conſider (not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe now of the various Particles and alterations the circulating Liquors receive from the Air, by Inſpiration and otherwiſe; (for the nature of a Letter will not allow of ſuch Excurſions) that whether the Cauſe or <hi>Minera Morbi,</hi> lodge in the Blood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or <hi>Genus Nervoſum:</hi> Moſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Stomach and Guts, and the various alterations the materials of our Diet undergoes in theſe digeſtory Cavities; cannot vindicate themſelves to us, for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming their Duty ſo faintly; nor can we, to our ſelves, for oppreſſing and burthening them ſo much. So that if the <hi>Chyle</hi> be Acrious, Acid, Auſtere, or of other quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the Blood muſt participate of the nature of the materials of which it is made. Beſides, if a great deal of Crudities, Humours, or call them as you will, neſtle and ſtagnate in the <hi>Guts, Stomach,</hi> or other parts of the <hi>Abdomen,</hi> which vitiate the Chylification and <hi>Chyle,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:98852:8"/>and rivolets it ill to the circulating humours, by the <hi>lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic Veins</hi> (and if not carried off by Vomiters and Purgers according to the preſent Circumſtances of the Patient) <hi>in Limine,</hi> muſt give new matter to new recurring <hi>Parox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſms,</hi> till a long abſtinence, and oft recurring Fits, ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citates the Patient, and conſumes the <hi>fomies Morbi</hi> in the firſt Region; which a rational Phyſician can remove very ſoon, without the leaſt or very little trouble to the Patient; if Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement or Biaſs (<hi>the Brats of Authority</hi>) oblige the <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician</hi> to be a Spectator, the <hi>Patient</hi> is like to have a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant time of it.</p>
            <p>In my Practice, wherever I find the <hi>Minera Morbi,</hi> I tamper not with it, but turns it off how ſoon I can: and if I occaſion thereby any troubleſome Diſorder in the <hi>Fluids,</hi> I force them to their proper Stations, by ſuitable <hi>Paragoricks:</hi> by which Methods I never had any Diſrepu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, but my Patients great Advantage. When <hi>Indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> oblige, I cauſe open a Vein, I give <hi>Swetters</hi> and <hi>Diu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks,</hi> by which I divert the deſigned Courſe of thoſe troubleſom <hi>fluid Salts:</hi> and ſeeing the Animal Spirits are but the product of the Blood, and cannot be expected to be of a more mild temper than their Progenitor: I alter the circulating <hi>Fluids</hi> as ſoon, and much as I can, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving out of them what is hoſtile and troubleſome, and lodging in them ſuch Principles and Particles I judge them to want. And I judge, by ſuch a Method, (ſuppoſing ſtill the Patient to be rational and tractable) the Gout is not altogether ſo ſtubborn and rebellious as he is diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be; at leaſt, I found him (in ſuch circumſtances) obſequious enough to my Commands; ſo that I will not be ſo unjuſt to the poor Criminal as many are. For ſhould I not procure a tractable and rational Patient, what he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects, I would rather complain of my Timorouſneſs, my being impoſed on by the Bugbears of great Authority, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98852:9"/>negligence of ſuitable adminiſtrations, than on the ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornneſs of a few <hi>vicid, ſaline humors,</hi> may be cut off as to their <hi>Minera,</hi> and thrown off by ſuitable Medicines in a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhort time.</p>
            <p>Sir, I find you are irreconcilable to <hi>Topical Applications,</hi> whether <hi>Pultiſſes, Plaiſters, or all</hi> others of that kind: but when I have diſcourſed you a little as to the nature of thoſe kind Applications, I hope I may moderate your Paſſion againſt them; and do ſome of them the Honour as to procure them your moſt ſerene and obliging Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs to you, and acknowledge, that ſuch of them as are <hi>emplaſtick, astringent,</hi> and ſo contract the <hi>Pores,</hi> and ſtops the <hi>inſenſible tranſpiration,</hi> deſervedly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit very much your diſpleaſure, on the Grounds and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons you intimate in your Letter. But ſuch internal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications as open the <hi>Pores,</hi> diſſolves Coagulations, (by blunting the <hi>acid coagulating Salts</hi>) in the <hi>cutaneous Glans,</hi> and poſſibly alters very much the texture of the circula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Liquors, without any previous trouble to the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach) I hope I may preſume, to uſher thoſe to your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance: and I have that very great eſteem for your Merit, that I would not make you uneaſie, by giving your Eſteem and Friendſhip to any, but thoſe I can venture my reputation for what I promiſe in their Name. And if you command me to diſcloſe to you the very <hi>Secrets of my Cabinet,</hi> your Commands will be obſequiouſly obeyed.</p>
            <p>I do not much admire the Cuſtom of <hi>Holland;</hi> nor do I believe a Rational and Sedulous Phyſician (if the Patient be tractable) will ſuffer the <hi>Gout</hi> to run all theſe Stages; for I know by many Experiences, it may be ſtrangled when <hi>in embrio,</hi> or may be deſtroyed in the Bud, before it can bloſſome; or if it do, may be made fall before it ripen, <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lata cauſa tolitur effectus:</hi> but if we ſuffer our digeſtions to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98852:9"/>be leſed, vitiate, and oppreſſed, the circulating Liquors to be loaded with troubleſome Salts, or other particles; if we lodg and continue in the Center, and digeſting Cavities of our Body, ſuch a maſs of incommoding Humours, which muſt of neceſſity produce many Diſtempers, according to the Texture of the <hi>Fluids</hi> and particular <hi>Mechaniſms</hi> of the Solids of thoſe concerned; then the <hi>Holland</hi> Cuſtom takes place, and not only the <hi>Gout,</hi> but other Diſtempers, both <hi>Acute</hi> and <hi>Chronic,</hi> runs their particular Stages in great Triumph, which we owe to our own Inadvertency, or our Phyſicians neglect; for our Health and Sickneſſes are <hi>Mechanical,</hi> depend on <hi>Mechanical</hi> Principles; and he who underſtands this <hi>Mechaniſm</hi> well, and adverts atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively to all its Motions, Meaſures, and Stops, can order the bodily Machine ſo, that Opinions handed down to us from Antiquity, as to the Nature of Diſeaſes, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of Cure, will very ſoon and eaſily be antiquated with the ſerious Obſervers of what concerns Health and Sickneſs.</p>
            <p>I do not queſtion Perſons of both Sexes, who lived very temperately, as to the Solids and Liquids of their Diet, are originally (if I may ſo term it) obnoxious and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed for ſeveral particular Diſtempers, from which many (who are abſolute Slaves to their Palates, and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on all irregularities of that Nature, and are intimate to all ſort of Debauches) are exempted; but this depends moſtly on the primative Configurations, and <hi>Mechaniſms of the Glans, Tubulae,</hi> and other ſecretory Organs of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which are not framed at the ſame rate in all individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als; whether this difference of particular <hi>Mechaniſms,</hi> or <hi>Organizations,</hi> proceed from <hi>Hereditary</hi> (if the word may paſs) Principles, or from other ſuperior or concurrent Cauſes, I will not give you or my ſelf the trouble to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:98852:10"/>
            <p>This Letter will not allow me to give you my Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions on your Ingenious Speculations about the Nature of <hi>Fevers,</hi> and your placing them in their ſeveral Ranks and Claſſes, leſt I ſhould give you the trouble to read a <hi>Pamphlet</hi> inſtead of a <hi>Letter,</hi> which by its length is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come too bulcous already, and may rob you of too much of your time, which you always imploy to better pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; but if This pleaſe, that may be the Subject of a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Entertainment. You did me the kindneſs to read me ſome <hi>Eſſays</hi> you have yet kept in their Retirement; but in my Opinion they very much deſerve a better <hi>Fate;</hi> and I am confident, you will very much oblige the Learned part of Mankind, if you give them that dreſs, in which they may be in their hands. <hi>Sir,</hi> believe me, that none eſteems your ſelf, and the products of your Pen more, than</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very Humble Servant, <hi>J. GORDON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98852:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
